Well, good afternoon, everybody.
حسنًا، مساء الخير جميعًا.
Thank you all very much for coming along today.
شكرًا لكم جميعًا لحضوركم اليوم.
I'd like to begin my talk with a story.
أود أن أبدأ حديثي بقصة.
It's a story that begins, but does not end,
قصة لها بداية، ولكن ليس لها نهاية،
with a mathematician named Tim Gowers.
مع عالم رياضيات يُدعى تيم غاورز.
Gowers is one of the world's most renowned mathematicians.
يعتبر غاورز واحد من أشهر علماء الرياضيات في العالم.
He's a professor at Cambridge University
وهو أستاذ في جامعة كامبريدج
and a recipient of the Fields Medal,
ومتسلم ل "فيلدز ميدال"،
often called the Nobel Prize of mathematics.
والتي غالبًا ما يطلق عليها جائزة نوبل للرياضيات.
Gowers is also a blogger,
وغاورز أيضًا مدوّن،
and in January of 2009, he used his blog to pose a very striking question:
وفي يناير 2009، استخدم مدونته لطرح سؤال مثير للغاية:
Is massively collaborative mathematics possible?
هل الرياضيات التعاونية الضخمة ممكنة؟
So what he was proposing in this post
لذا ما كان يقترحه في منشوره
was to use his blog to attack a difficult unsolved mathematical problem --
كان استخدام مدونته لمواجهة مشكلة رياضية صعبة،
a problem which he said he would "love to solve" --
مشكلة قال أنه من دواعي سروره أن يحلها
completely in the open,
تمامًا في العلن،
using his blog to post his ideas and his partial progress.
باستخدام مدونته لنشر أفكاره وتقدمه الجزئي.
What's more, he issued an open invitation,
ما هو أكثر من ذلك، أنه أصدر دعوة مفتوحة،
inviting anybody in the world who thought that they had an idea to contribute
يدعوا فيها أي شخص في العالم لديه فكرة للمساهمة
to post their idea in the comment section of the blog.
لنشر فكرتهم في خانة التعليق في المدونة.
His hope was that by combining the ideas of many minds,
وأمله أن بإدماج أفكار العديد من العقول،
he could make easy work of his hard mathematical problem.
يمكنه أن يجعل العمل سهل لمشكلته الرياضية الصعبة.
He called this experiment the Polymath Project.
وسمى هذه التجربة بمشروع "بولي ماث."
Well, the Polymath Project got off to a slow start.
حسنًا، بدأ مشروع "بولي ماث" ببداية بطيئة.
In the first seven hours, nobody posted any comments.
في الساعات السبع الأولى، لم ينشر أحد أي تعليق.
But then, a mathematician from the University of British Columbia
ولكن بعد ذلك، قام عالم رياضيات من جامعة كولومبيا البريطانية
named Jozsef Solymosi
يُدعى جوزيف سوليموزي
posted a short comment.
بنشر تعليق قصير.
And this seemed to break the ice, because a few minutes later,
وبدا هذا ككسر الجليد، لأن بعد بضع بدقائق،
a high school teacher named Jason Dyer posted a suggestion.
قام معلم في مدرسة ثانوية يدعى جايسون داير بنشر اقتراح.
And a few minutes after that,
وبعد ذلك ببضع دقائق،
another mathematician named Terence Tao, also a Fields medalist,
قام عالم رياضيات آخر يدعى تيرينس تاو، وهو حائز أيضًا على ميدالية "فيلدز،"
posted an idea.
بنشر فكرة.
And things really started to move quickly at this point.
وبدأت الأمور تمضي بسرعة في هذه المرحلة.
Over the next 37 days,
خلال الأيام ال 37 القادمة،
27 different people would post 800 substantive comments
سيقوم 27 شخص مختلف بنشر 800 تعليق حقيقي
containing 170,000 words.
يحتوي على 170 ألف كلمة.
I was not a serious participant, but I was following along closely
لم أكن مشاركًا جادًا، ولكن كنتُ أتابع عن كثب
from the start,
من البداية،
and it was just amazing.
وكان ذلك مذهلًا.
The speed with which an idea would be tentatively proposed
السرعة التي يتم اقتراح فكرة
and then really rapidly developed by other people and improved,
ثم تطويرها وتحسينها بسرعة من قبل آخرون،
sometimes discarded --
يتم التخلي عنها أحيانًا.
it was just amazing.
وكان ذلك مذهلًا جدًا.
Gowers described the process
وصف غاورز العملية
as being to ordinary research "as driving is to pushing a car."
أنها بحث عادي "حيث أن القيادة هي دفع السيارة"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
At the end of the 37 days,
في نهاية ال 37 يوم،
Gowers used his blog to announce that they had solved the core problem;
استخدم غاورز مدونته للإعلان أنهم حلوا المشكلة الأساسية؛
in fact, they had solved a harder generalization of the problem.
في الحقيقة، لقد حلوا جزءًا أصعب من المشكلة.
The Polymath Project had succeeded.
لقد نجح مشروع "بولي ماث."
So what the Polymath Project suggests, at least to me,
لذا فإن ما يقترحه مشروع "بولي ماث،" على الأقل بالنسبة لي،
is that we can use the internet to build tools
أنه يمكننا استخدام شبكة الإنترنت لتصميم أدوات
that actually expand our ability
تزيد من قدرتنا
to solve the most challenging intellectual problems.
لحل معظم المشكلات الفكرية الأكثر تحديًا.
Or, to put it in another way:
أو بعبارة أخرى:
we can build tools which actively amplify our collective intelligence
نستطيع بناء أدوات تزيد من ذكائنا
in much the same way as, for millennia, we've used physical tools
بنفس الطريقة التي استخدمنا فيها الأدوات المادية لآلآف السنين
to amplify our strength.
لتضخيم قوتنا.
OK?
حسنًا؟
So what I'd like to talk about today, or what I'd like to explore today,
إذن ما أود الحديث عنه اليوم، أو ما أود استكشافه اليوم،
is what this means for science.
هو ما يعنيه هذا للعلم.
It's much more important than just solving a single mathematical problem.
إنه أهم بكثير من مجرد حل مشكلة رياضية واحدة.
It means an expansion in the range of scientific problems
إذ يعني توسع في نطاق المشكلات العلمية
we can hope to attack at all.
التي نأمل في مواجهتها جميعًا.
It means, potentially, an acceleration in the rate of scientific discovery.
يعني احتمال تسارع معدل الاكتشافات العلمية.
It means a change in the way we construct knowledge itself.
ويعني ذلك تغيير في الطريقة التي نبني بها المعرفة.
So, before I get too overexcited, however,
لذا، قبل أن أتحمس بشدة،
I would like to talk about some of the challenges,
أود التحدث عن بعض التحديات،
some of the problems.
وبعض المشكلات.
Particularly, I'd like to describe a failure of this approach.
تحديدًا، أود أن أصف فشل هذا المنهج.
It occurred in 2005, or started in 2005.
حدث ذلك في 2005، أو بدأ في عام 2005.
A grad student at Caltech named John Stockton had a very good idea
كان لدى طالب دراسات عليا يُدعى جون ستوكتون فكرة جيدة
for what he called the "Quantum Wiki,"
لما أسماه "كوانتام ويكي،"
or "Qwiki" for short.
أو "كويكي" بشكل مختصر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
OK? It's a great idea.
حسنًا؟ إنها فكرة عظيمة.
What he did with the Qwiki was --
كان ما فعله مع "الكويكي" ..
the idea of the Qwiki was that it was going to be a great repository
الفكرة من "الكويكي" أنه كان سيكون مستودعًا عظيمًا
of human knowledge,
للمعرفة البشرية،
much like Wikipedia.
مثل ويكيبيديا.
But instead of being focused on general knowledge,
ولكن بدلًا من التركيز على العلوم العامة،
it was going to be focused on specialist knowledge in quantum computing.
كان سيركز على المعرفة المتخصصة في الحوسبة الكمية.
It was going be kind of a supertextbook for the field,
كان ذلك نوعًا من الكتب في المجال
with information about all the latest research,
مع معلومات عن أحدث الأبحاث،
about what the big open problems in the field were,
وعن المشكلات الكبيرة في المجال،
people's speculation about how to solve the problems,
وتوقعات الناس حول كيفية حل المشكلات،
and so on.
وما إلى ذلك.
Like Wikipedia, the intention was that it would be written by the users,
ومثل ويكيبيديا، كان المقصد كتابتها من قِبل المستخدمين،
in this case, by experts in quantum computing.
في هذه الحالة، من قِبل الخبراء في الحوسبة الكمية.
I was present at the conference at Caltech in 2005, when it was announced.
كنتُ حاضرًا في المؤتمر في معهد كاليفورنيا للتكنولوجيا 2005، عندما أُعلن عنه.
And some of the people who I spoke to were very skeptical,
وبعض الأشخاص الذين تحدثت معهم كانوا متشككين للغاية،
but some of the people were very excited by the idea.
ولكن البعض الآخر كانوا متحمسين جدًا للفكرة.
They were impressed by the implementation;
لقد أُعجبوا بالتنفيذ؛
they were impressed by the amount of initial seed material
وأُعجبوا بكمية مادة البذور الأولية
which had been put on the site;
التي تم وضعها على الموقع؛
and most of all, they were excited by the vision.
والأهم من ذلك كله، كانوا متحمسين للرؤية.
But just because they were excited,
ولكن لمجرد أنهم كانوا متحمسين،
didn't mean they wanted to take the time themselves to contribute.
لا يعني ذلك أنهم يريدون المساهمة.
They hoped that other people would do so.
كانوا يأملون أن أناس آخرون يقومون بذلك.
And in the end, nobody, essentially,
وفي النهاية، لم يكن أحد، في الأساس،
was really all that interested in contributing.
مهتمًا بالمساهمة حقًا.
If you look today, except in a few small corners,
وبالنظر لليوم، بإستثناء زوايا صغيرة،
the Qwiki is essentially dead.
فإن ال "ويكي" أساسًا ميت.
And, sad to say, this is quite a common story.
ومن المحزن أن نقول بأن هذه القصة شائعة.
Many scientists, in fields ranging from genetics to string theory,
العديد من العلماء في المجالات تبدأ من علم الوراثة حتى نظرية الأوتار
have tried to start science wikis along very similar lines.
حاولوا البدء بعلم "الويكيات" بطريقة مشابهة.
And typically, they've failed for essentially the same reason.
وقد فشلوا، بشكل نمطي، لنفس السبب.
It's not just science wikis, either.
وهذا ليس فقط علم "ويكي".
Inspired by Facebook,
وبإلهام من الفيسبوك،
many organizations have tried to create social networks for scientists,
حاولت العديد من المنظمات صناعة شبكة اجتماعية للعلماء،
which will connect scientists to other people with similar interests.
التي ستربط العلماء بأشخاص آخرين لديهم اهتمامات متشابهة.
So they can share things like data or code, their ideas and so on.
حتى يتمكنوا من مشاركة أمور مثل البيانات أو الرموز وأفكارهم وما إلى ذلك.
Again, it sounds like a good idea.
يبدو وكأنها فكرة جيدة.
But if you join one of these sites,
ولكن إذا انضممت إلى أحد هذه المواقع،
you'll quickly discover that they're essentially empty.
ستكتشف سريعًا أنهم أساسًا فارغين.
They're virtual ghost towns.
إنها مدن وهمية.
So what's going on? What's the problem here?
إذن ماذا يحدث؟ ما المشكلة هنا؟
Why are these promising sites failing?
ما هذه المواقع الواعدة؟
Well, imagine that you're an ambitious young scientist.
تخيل أنك عالم شاب طموح.
In fact, I know some of you here are ambitious young scientists.
حقيقةً، أعلم أن بعضكم علماء صغار طموحين.
You really would like to get a job -- a permanent job, a good job --
ستحصل على وظيفة دائمة وجيدة
doing the work that you love.
وتقوم بعمل تحبه.
But it's incredibly competitive to get such jobs.
ولكن هناك منافسة في الحصول على مثل هذه الوظيفة.
Often, there'll be hundreds of very highly qualified applicants for positions.
عادةً، سيكون هناك المئات من المقدمين المؤهلين لهذا المنصب.
And so you find yourself working 60, 70, 80 hours a week,
ولذا ستجد نفسك تعمل 60 و70 و80 ساعة في الأسبوع،
doing the one thing that you know will get you such a job,
بعمل الشيء الوحيد الذي تفعله ستحصل على مثل هذه الوظيفة،
and that is writing scientific papers.
وهو كتابة أوراق علمية.
You may think that the Qwiki is a wonderful idea in principle,
قد تعتقد أن "ويكي" فكرة هائلة من حيث المبدأ،
but you also know that writing a single mediocre paper
ولكن تعلم أيضًا أن كتابة ورقة واحدة متوسطة المستوى
will do much more for your career and your job prospects
ستفعل الكثير لمسيرتك المهنية وفرصة عملك
than a long series of brilliant contributions to such a site.
أكثر من سلسلة طويلة من الإسهامات الرائعة لمثل هذا الموقع.
So even though you may like the idea
وحتى لو كنت قد أعجبت بالفكرة
and you may think it will advance science more quickly,
وتعتقد أنها ستطور العلم بسرعة أكبر،
you find you just can't conceive of it as being part of your job.
ستجد أنك لا تستطيع تصور أنها جزء من وظيفتك.
It's not.
فهي ليست كذلك.
The only things which can succeed in this kind of environment
الأشياء الوحيدة التي تستطيع أن تنجح في مثل هذه البيئة
are projects like the Polymath Project,
هي المشاريع مثل مشروع "بولي ماث،"
which, even though they employ an unconventional means to an end,
وعلى الرغم من أنهم يوظفون وسائل غير تقليدية لتحقيق هدف،
they have an essential conservatism about them.
فإن لديهم المبادئ الأساسية حولها.
The end product of the Polymath Project was still a scientific paper.
كان المنتج النهائي لمشروع "بولي ماث" لا يزال ورقة علمية.
In fact, it was several papers. Right?
في الحقيقة، لقد كان عدة أوراق. أليس كذلك؟
So unconventional means, but conventional ends.
إذن الأدوات غير تقليدية، ولكن الأهداف تقليدية،
So there's a kind of conservatism about it.
لذا هناك نوع من المحافظة حول هذا الموضوع.
And don't get me wrong -- the Polymath Project is terrific,
ولا تفهموني بطريقة خاطئة، إن مشروع "بولي ماث" رائع،
but it is a pity that scientists can only use tools
ولكن من المؤسف أن العلماء ليس باستطاعتهم سوى استخدام أدوات
which have this kind of conservative nature.
لديها نوع من الطبيعة المقاومة للتغيير.
So let me tell you a story about an instance
لذا دعوني أخبركم قصة عن حالة
where we moved away from this conservatism.
ابتعدنا فيها عن هذا التيار المقاوم للتغيير والمحافظ
It's a rare story where the conservatism has been broken.
إنها قصة نادرة تم فيها كسر هذا التيار المحافظ.
It occurred in the 1990s, when, as you know,
حدث ذلك في التسعينيات، عندما، كما تعلمون
for the first time, biologists were taking large amounts of genetic data
قام علماء الأحياء ولأول مرة بأخذ كميات ضخمة من البيانات الوراثية
to collect in the Human Genome Project.
لجمعها في مشروع الجينوم البشري.
And there were sites online
وكان هناك مواقع على شبكة الإنترنت
which would allow biologists to upload that data
التي تسمح لعلماء الأحياء برفع البيانات
so it could be shared with other people around the world
ومشاركتها مع أشخاص من أرجاء العالم
and analyzed by other people.
وتحليلها من قبل آخرين.
Probably the best known of these is the site GenBank,
وربما يكون أشهرها موقع "جِن بانك"،
which some of you may have heard of or used.
والذي ربما سمع به بعضكم أو استخدمه.
And these sites, like GenBank,
وهذه المواقع، مثل "جِن بانك"،
had the problem in common with Qwiki that scientists -- they're not paid
لديهم مشكلة مشتركة مع "ويكي" وهي أن العلماء... لا يتم الدفع لهم
or rewarded for sharing their data.
أو مكافأتهم مقابل مشاركة بياناتهم.
It's all about publishing papers.
إن الأمر كله يتعلق بنشر الأوراق.
So there was a considerable reluctance to actually upload the data.
لذلك كان هناك تردد كبير لرفع البيانات.
Yet, everybody could see that this was silly --
الآن، قد يرى الجميع أن هذا الأمر كان سخيفًا.
it was obvious that this was the right thing to do.
فقد كان واضحًا أن هذا هو الشيء الصحيح الذي يجب عمله
But just because it was obvious
ولكن كونه مجرد واضح
didn't mean that people were actually doing it.
لم يعني أن الناس كانوا يقومون بذلك بالفعل.
So a meeting was convened in Bermuda in 1996
لذا عُقد اجتماع في برمودا عام 1996
of many of the world's leading molecular biologists.
للعديد من العلماء الرائدين في الأحياء الجزئية من أنحاء العالم.
And they sat and they discussed the problem for several days,
وجلسوا وناقشوا المشكلة لعدة أيام،
and they came up with what are now called the Bermuda Principles,
وابتكروا ما يعرف به حاليًا "مبادئ برمودا،"
which state that:
التي تنص على الآتي:
first, once human genetic data is taken in the lab,
أولًا: بمجرد أخذ البيانات الوراثية البشرية إلى المختبر،
it should be immediately uploaded
يجب أن يتم رفعها فورًا
to a site like GenBank;
لموقع مثل "جِن بانك."
and two, that the data would be in the public domain.
وثانيًا: أن البيانات ستكون على نطاق عام.
And these principles were given teeth,
وهذه المبادئ
because they were taken by the big scientific grant agencies --
لأنها أُخذت من قِبل وكالات المنح العالمية ...
the US National Institutes of Health, the UK Wellcome Trust --
مثل "معهد الولايات المتحدة للصحة" و"ويلكم ترتست البريطانية"
and actually baked into policy.
وتم اخضاعها في السياسة.
So it meant that if you were a scientist who wanted to work on the human genome,
لذا هذا يعني إذا كنت عالِمًا يريد العمل على الجينوم البشري،
you had to agree to abide by these principles.
يجب عليك الموافقة بالإلتزام بهذه المبادئ.
And today, I'm very pleased to say, as a result,
واليوم، يسعدني جدًا أن أقول، نتيجة لذلك،
you can go online -- anybody here -- and download the human genome.
يمكنكم الذهاب على شبكة الإنترنت وتحميل الجينوم البشري.
So that's a terrific story.
إنها قصة رائعة.
But the human genome is just a tiny, tiny fraction
ولكن الجينوم البشري ماهو إلا جزء صغير جدًا
of all scientific knowledge.
من المعرفة العلمية.
Even just in other parts of genetics,
حتى في الأجزاء الأخرى من علم الوراثة
there is so much knowledge that is still locked up.
هناك كم هائل من المعرفة التي لا تزال غير معلومة.
I spoke with one bioinformatician
لقد تحدثت مع أحد الخبراء في استخدام المعلومات الحيوية
who told me that he'd been "sitting on the genome of an entire species
الذي أخبرني أنه "عكف على جينوم بكافة أنواعه
for more than a year."
لأكثر من سنة."
An entire species.
نوع كامل.
And in other parts of science,
وفي أجزاء أخرى من العلم،
it is routine that scientists hoard their data.
إنه أمر روتيني أن يخزن العلماء بياناتهم.
They hoard the computer code that they write
إنهم يخزنون رمز الكمبيوتر الذي يكتبونه
that could be useful, potentially, to other people.
والذي من الممكن أن يكون مفيدًا لأشخاص آخرين.
They hoard their best ideas.
إنهم يخزنون أفضل أفكارهم.
And they often hoard even the descriptions of the problems
وغالبًا ما يخزنون حتى أوصاف للمشكلات
that they think are most interesting.
التي يعتقدون أنها الأكثر أهمية.
And so, what I and other people in the Open Science movement
لذا، أنا والآخرون في حركة العلوم المفتوحة
would like to do is,
ما نود القيام به،
we'd like to change this situation.
هو أننا نريد تغيير هذا الوضع.
We would like to change the culture of science
نود تغيير ثقافة العلوم
so that scientists become much more strongly motivated
بحيث يصبح العلماء متحفزين بشدة
to share all of these different kinds of knowledge.
لمشاركة جميع الأنواع المختلفة من المعرفة.
We want to change the values of individual scientists
نريد أن نغير قيم العلماء
so they start to see it as part of their job
حتى يبدأوا بالنظر إليها كجزء من وظيفتهم
to be sharing their data, to be sharing their code,
لمشاركة بياناتهم، ومشاركة رموزهم،
to be sharing their best ideas and their problems.
لمشاركة أفضل أفكارهم ومشاكلهم.
So, if we can do this, this kind of change in values,
وإذا تمكنا القيام بهذا، هذا النوع من التغيير في القيم،
then we will indeed start to see individual scientists rewarded
حينها سنبدأ بالفعل في رؤية العلماء يُكافأون
for doing these things;
للقيام بهذه الأمور؛
there will be incentives to do them.
سيكون هناك حوافز للقيام بذلك.
It's a difficult thing to do, however.
ومع ذلك، من الصعب القيام بذلك.
We're talking about changing the culture of entire large parts of science.
نحن نتحدث عن تغيير ثقافة أجزاء كبيرة من العلم.
But it has happened before once in history,
وقد حدث هذا من قبل في التاريخ،
right back at the dawn of science.
بالعودة إلى فجر العلم.
Galileo, 1609: he points his telescope up at the sky towards Saturn,
غاليلو عام 1609: يشير بتلسكوبه نحو السماء باتجاه زحل،
and he sees for the first time in history
ويرى لأول مرة في التاريخ
what we now know are the rings of Saturn.
ما نسميه اليوم حلقات زحل.
Does he tell everybody in the world?
هل أخبر الجميع في العالم؟
No, he doesn't do that.
كلا، لم يفعل ذلك.
He writes down a description, privately,
إذ كتب وصفًا بشكل سري،
and then he scrambles the letters in the description into an anagram,
ثم قام بخلط الرسائل في الوصف إلى كلمات بترتيب أحرف مختلف،
and he sends that anagram to several of his astronomer rivals.
وقام بإرسال تلك الكلمات إلى منافسيه الفلكيين.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And what this ensures is that, if they later make the same discovery,
وهذا ما يضمن أنه إذا اكتشفوا فيما بعد نفس الاكتشاف
he can reveal the anagram and get the credit,
سيتمكن من الكشف عن الكلمات الذي قام بتغيير ترتيب أحرفها ويحصل على الاعتراف،
but in the meantime, he hasn't given up any knowledge at all.
ولكن في نفس الوقت، لم يتنازل عن أي معرفة على الإطلاق.
And I'm sad to say that he was not uncommon at the time:
ويؤسفني أن أقول أن ذلك كان شائعًا في ذلك الوقت:
Newton, Huygens, Hooke, Leonardo -- they all used similar devices.
إذ استخدم نيوتن وهيوغنز وليناردو مثل هذه الطرق.
OK?
حسنًأ؟
The printing press had been around for 150 years by this time.
كانت المطبعة موجودة قبل هذا الوقت ب 150 سنة.
And yet, there was a great battle in the 17th and 18th centuries
ومع ذلك كان هناك معركة كبيرة في القرن السابع عشر والثامن عشر
to change the culture of science,
لتغيير ثقافة العلم،
so that it became expected that when a scientist made a discovery,
وأصبح من المتوقع أنه إذا قام عالِم باكتشافٍ ما،
they would reveal it in a journal.
سيكشفون عنه في صحيفة.
Now, that's great that that change has happened. It's terrific.
الآن، هذا أمر عظيم
But today, we have new technologies,
ولكن اليوم، لدينا تقنيات حديثة،
we have new opportunities to share our knowledge in new ways
ولدينا فرص جديدة لمشاركة معرفتنا بطرق حديثة
and the ability to create tools
والقدرة لصناعة أدوات
that actually allow us to solve problems in entirely new ways.
تسمح لنا بالفعل لحل المشكلات بطرق جديدة تمامًا.
So we need to have a second open science revolution.
لذلك نحتاج أن نقوم بثورة أخرى لعلمٍ مفتوح.
It is my belief
أعتقد أن
that any publicly funded science should be open science.
أي علم تموله الدولة يجب أن يكون علمًا مفتوحًا.
How can we achieve this change?
كيف بإمكاننا تحقيق هذا التغيير؟
Well, if you're a scientist -- and I know many of you are not scientists,
حسنًا، إذا كنت عالِمًا، وأعلم أن الكثير منكم ليسوا بعلماء،
but if you are a scientist,
ولكن إذا كنت عالِمًا،
then there are things that you can do.
فهناك أشياء يمكنك القيام بها.
You can get involved in an open science project,
يمكنك المشاركة في مشروع علمي مفتوح،
even if it's just for a small fraction of your time.
حتى لو بجزء صغير من وقتك.
You can find forums online
يمكنك العثور على منتديات على شبكة الإنترنت
where you can share your knowledge in new ways,
حيث يمكنك مشاركة معرفتك بطرق جديدة،
ways that allow other people to build on that knowledge.
طرق تسمح للآخرين بالبناء على تلك المعرفة.
You can also, if you're more ambitious,
بإمكانك أيضًا، إذا كنت طموحًا أكثر،
start an open science project of your own.
البدء بمشروع علمي مفتوح خاص بك.
If you're really bold, you may wish to experiment
وإذا كنت جريئًا حقًا، ربما ترغب بتجربة
with entirely new ways of collaborating,
طرق جديدة تمامًا للتعاون،
in much the same way as the Polymath Project did.
كما فعل مشروع "بولي ماث."
But above all, what you should do is be very generous in giving credit
ولكن قبل كل شيء، مايتوجب عليك فعله هو أن تكون كريمًا في إعطاء الفضل
to those of your colleagues who are practicing science in the open
لزملائك الذين يمارسون العلم على نطاق مفتوح
and to promote their work.
وتعزيز عملهم.
It is only conservative scientific values
إنها فقط القيم المحافِظة
that look down on these activities -- the sharing of data, the blogging,
التي تقلل من قيمة هذه الأنشطة- مشاركة البينات والتدوين،
or using of wikis and so on.
أو استخدام "الويكي" وما إلى ذلك.
You can reject those conservative values
بإمكانك رفض هذه القيم المحافظة
and engage your scientific colleagues in conversation
وإشراك زملائك العلميين في محادثة
to promote the value of these new ways of working,
لتعزيز قيم العمل الجديدة،
to emphasize that it takes bravery to do these things,
للتأكيد على أن لعمل هذه الأمور فإنك بحاجة للشجاعة،
particularly by young scientists.
بالأخص من قِبل العلماء الشباب.
It's through such conversation that the culture of science can be changed.
من خلال تلك المحادثة فإن ثقافة العلم يمكن أن تتغير.
So if you are not a scientist,
لذا إذا لم تكن عالِم،
there are also things that you can do.
هناك أيضًا أمور يمكنك القيام بها.
My belief is that the single most important thing that we can do
أعتقد أن أهم شيء يمكننا القيام به
to give impetus to open science
لإعطاء دافع للعلم المفتوح
is to create a general awareness amongst the population
هو خلق وعي عام بين السكان
of the issue of open science and of its critical importance.
للمشاكل التي تتعلق بالعلم المفتوح وأهميتها الشديدة.
If there is that general awareness,
إذا كان هناك وعي عام،
then the scientific community will inevitably find --
عندها سيجد المجتمع العلمي حتمًا...
it will be dragged by the population at large
سيجره السكان بشكل عام
in the right direction.
إلى الاتجاه الصحيح.
There are simple things you can do.
هناك أشياء بسيطة يمكنك فعلها.
You can talk to your friends and acquaintances who are scientists
يمكنك التحدث مع أصدقائك ومعارفك من العلماء
and just ask them what are they doing to work more openly.
فقط إسألهم ماذا يفعلون لكي يعملون بشكل أكثر انفتاحًا.
Or you can use your imagination and your personal power
أو يمكنك استخدام خيالك وقوتك الشخصية
to raise awareness in other ways.
لزيادة الوعي بطرق أخرى.
We're talking about changing not just what scientists do
نحن لانتحدث فقط عن تغيير مايقوم به العلماء
but what grant agencies do,
ولكن ما تقوم به وكالات المنح،
what universities do and what governments do.
ما تقوم به الجامعات وما تقوم به الحكومات.
And you can influence all of those things.
وبإمكانك إحداث تأثير في جميع تلك الأشياء.
Our society faces a fundamental question:
مجتمعنا يواجه سؤال أساسي:
What kinds of knowledge are we going to expect
ما نوع المعرفة التي نتوقعها
and incentivize our scientists to share?
وتُحفز علماءنا للمشاركة؟
Will we continue as we have done in the past?
هل سنستمر على ما قمنا به سابقًا؟
Or will we embrace new kinds of sharing,
أو أننا سنحتضن طرق أخرى من المشاركة،
which lead to new methods for solving problems
التي ستؤدي إلى طرق حديثة لحل المشكلات
and an acceleration in the process of science,
وتسارع في عملية العلم،
entirely across the board?
تمامًا في جميع المجالات؟
My hope is that we will embrace open science
أملي أننا سنحتضن العلم المفتوح
and really seize this opportunity that we have
ونوسع الفرصة التي نمتلكها
to reinvent discovery itself.
لإعادة اكتشاف الاكتشاف نفسه.
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرًا لكم. (تصفيق)